[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right peter's here so we'll begin
um good morning everyone uh welcome to
the stoa
i'm peter limberg the steward of the
stoa there still is a place for us to go
here and dialogue
about what matters most at the nice edge
of this very moment
and today we have peter wang
entrepreneur former physicist
and student of the human condition so
peter is a sense maker in residence
in the stoa for the month of september
this is a four session series happening
over four weeks
uh same time same day uh on a theme
and we had uh john robb previously uh
since making residents in august we
currently have dave snowden
and zack stein this month as well daniel
schmuckenberger nora benson
even james carson from finite infant
game might come in to be a sense maker
in residence in upcoming months
so this is a pretty exciting series and
this one
the theme is um about mental models
uh so peter suggested uh he has a slew
of these mental models that he uses to
navigate
the complexity of life from selfhood
relationships communications and systems
um so throughout the series the idea was
to chat about it
um as a group and so we can have some
kind of coherency throughout the month
so how today is going to work uh i'll
take peter
peter in a moment and imagine uh we
either share your thoughts on the
whatever you have presented today peter
we can have an interview style it's up
to you
uh if you have any questions for peter
throughout throw it in the the chat box
um this will go on youtube so if you
don't wanna be on youtube uh just
indicate that and i'll read it on your
behalf
uh if not i'll call on you and you'll
mute yourself
um that being said uh peter
how's it going you're muted
hi yes sorry jumping in a little bit
just a couple minutes late here but um
but yes it's going well i've been uh
i've been looking forward to this and i
i enjoyed my my previous
session my previous visit here uh on the
stoa and um i'm really looking forward
to this so i'm very honored to have been
invited
back i didn't you know proved some value
i guess to people
the first time around but i'm really
looking forward to this and i actually
this has been a really wonderful
um opportunity for me to just write down
like a lot of the stuff that's kind of
in my head so i think that was also
it's a good forcing function as we call
it in physics so um
and so function is a good mental model
as well versus function is also a mental
model that's right
yeah so how would you like uh today to
go uh do you have some thoughts to share
and then uh
yes i i would have a little a few slides
i would i could present and i could
speak to them and just kind of
um yeah well let's do it that way and
then
i was going to kind of do it live and
give people kind of choose your own
adventure kind of thing
this is our first one and maybe the the
next uh several will be more structured
but um
but yeah so let me go ahead and share my
can i share my screen yeah give you
access
i can great thank you okay
so um
so when peter first oh what's going on
here my
is my computer zoom really eats my cpu
okay okay so
um my mental model so peter first
approached me about this concept i was
thinking wow that would be
fantastic but what am i going to talk
about um i don't
actually have such a large body of
written work
um as uh in interviews and things like
that that you you know
you have people like daniel or or um uh
i guess schmackenberger or thorson or
whoever
um of course a lot of other people like
john rob who you know they have
just a fantastic constant stream of
output for me it's
it's i've just been thinking about this
stuff for a while about all of it
kind of this stuff and i thought that um
it would be useful to just go through
and talk about you know the the various
lenses i used to look at
things so this um set of presentations
hold on
my mouse just disappeared and i know how
to get it back
okay well let's just uh start with this
so the way i think about this is that
these sessions uh
in september is going to be somewhat
like a whole earth catalog sort of uh
you know here are the various tools i
use to think about things um
and it's also a little bit of a you know
here's my bestiary right all the
wonderful
you know sometimes little quirky things
sometimes big things that i've
encountered in my
in my journey um and uh and the idea
here is
hopefully other people can find them
useful and one grand disclaimer all over
all of this is that i do not claim to be
an expert
on many of these topics i i think you
know we're gonna kind of flow through
uh a number of different things and i'll
be sharing kind of what i've learned
about them and how i see them
but many of you on the call may be much
deeper in some of these topics than i am
and so please
if you feel like there's something i'm
missing about it or some way that a
connects to be that i'm not picking up
on
i'd love to learn about that from from
you all um so why this topic right
i do believe that the easy mode of sense
making is over
um and uh what that means is that
um the world is getting more dangerous
um or
rather the stakes are getting higher for
people who have bad sense making
and um all of the easy you can reach for
it and grab it and like yeah i believe
that narrative right that kind of makes
sense to me
um those things all are starting to feel
cheesy
for most of us right it's starting to
feel like wow that's like basic
i guess it's not proper to say karen as
a as a pejorative but you know
from a medic standpoint someone on 4chan
might say oh that's basic care and sense
making right
um and so we all feel that like oh
that's kind of cheesy sense making what
do i even believe that um you know the
mega crowd would say well that's fake
news because everything's fake news
and it's true everything is fake news
most of reality that we live in is inner
subjective so
but but in any case the point is that um
we are we are now in
a much frothier uh water
and and so that easy mode is over um i
also realized that
my personal perspectives come from uh a
weird combination of things and so
when i have conversations uh like the
ones that we'll be having here on the
stowa but also
um just in my personal life and in
person with friends and whatnot
um i'll sometimes sometimes say things
and people say wow peter that's very
interesting that's a you know haven't
thought about that way and to me it
seems very natural
and so i'm interested in understanding
you know how is it that i came to some
of these perspectives
um and uh and so getting it all down on
paper
is is helpful and lastly sharing is
caring
um ultimately you know if you uh look at
the the
[Music]
the things that people involved in kind
of the game b
world and the infinite game world um
kind of the spirit that we carry is that
if we share with each other we learn
from each other
um we all get smarter right there is a
generativity to this
so how did i get here well
um in 2016 uh those of you who are
connected to or aware of american
politics might
remember that some stuff went down in
2016. and actually it was throughout the
course of that year
that i began thinking more about the
philosophy of technology and actually
how technology connects to society
i was starting to feel out of sorts with
some of the technology trends happening
in my little corner of the world
around open source and data science
machine learning um as well as
understanding how the business world
works
um understanding how the capital markets
work and and getting deeper on that as
as i developed as an entrepreneur and so
these things intersected
and i kind of went i would say my
journey really started kind of in that
first half of 2016
and i discovered that if i started
asking questions and pulling on threads
there's a great depth uh great uh
sorry
hello i think someone just accidentally
turned off mute uh oh okay sorry no
worries yeah um
so what i what i realized is that on any
thread that i pulled there was a great
intellectual depth behind there and
there's some very deep thinking
and moreover if you were to kind of poke
into all these different little areas
there were some deeper threads that
connected those together and i was very
interested in that that kind of nerd
sniped the physicist to me
so i started mapping out like you know
what are these different things you know
i had
um a whole thing i written up about the
web we lost
um also right off the election i started
doing a little blog post series about
trying to
apply the udo loop to making sense of
what was going on i gave a talk at an
unconference in january of 20
of uh 2017 that's where i actually met
jordan
uh hall for the first time i met a
number of other people who are kind of
in this space
now that i consider my friends kind of
in the game b world and
um and so that's kind of my personal
journey i'm very new to a lot of these
things
is i guess what i would say um but i'm
i'm deeply interested in their deep
connections
and you'll see the book there uh debt uh
the first five thousand years by david
graber the late unfortunately late david
graber who just passed away so rest in
peace
um but there's many you know good works
some older some younger that that all
intersect and so i just put it out there
as kind of a
brain tump of um a
kind of like one layer of the bestiary
and
these are topics concepts i could
probably do a half hour long talk on any
of these things
at least even for some of these a half
hour be just skimming the surface
um and moreover they all intersect and
there's a gordian knot of these things
all intersecting with each other
some of these things may be quite
familiar to some of you some of them may
be very unfamiliar
but i assure you that this is a how many
one two three four five
six seven eight nine ten eleven twelve
thirteen fourteen fifteen by three
yeah between 40 to 50 um topic
or 40 to 50 flay or flavored layer cake
and every flavor adds something
different it's actually
really interesting how each of these
things tied to the others
um and so these are
these are what i would call sort of
nodes or or
deeper concepts or theories or a little
body of work on it themselves
um some things are like a philosopher's
entire body of work like
jacques lowell talks about totalizing
technology um and he has a very large
body of work there's people who just
their entire academic career studying
what he says
and there's other things which is like a
blog post right or a rich
series of blog posts um for instance
gervais theory
by um by uh venkat rao
um and so there's all of these things
but they all come together they all
like it's it's when you put all these
lenses together and you look at the
world
through 50 different at 50 different
frequencies you see a richer set of
things than if you look at just two or
three
and beyond that there's additional
topics that are
maybe they're not giant nodes under
themselves but they are either
directly tied to some concrete dynamic
uh other thing in the world
or they are a particularly interesting
trajectory through this like you know 50
100 dimensional space of topics
um that i guess i could also talk about
so um that i would say
sets up kind of the here you know here's
here's the thing here's all of these
different things
uh here's the bestiary of ideas i had
prepared a couple of slides in advance
to talk through um oh can i not go back
oh my mouse is back okay hold on
there it is um uh i was thinking
starting the upper left here
on the metaphysics of quality and how
that touches
um the the sense of self and the super
what i call the superpositional identity
that also can tag on to things like the
keegan models of development as well as
um
you know metzinger's theory of
consciousness the perceptual self model
um these kinds of things and i think
that is a good
starting point to talk about to anchor a
lot of these other discussions
um but we can just ignore that all
together and talk about these other
things just in their own right and their
interactions with each other
so you know that's the i'll just put it
out there
what do you guys think peter like you
know please uh i am
i'm your piano to play with like 50 keys
here so
um i guess i'll throw back at you what
would be most interesting for you to
explore and and what way to explore it
and how to leverage sort of the
collective intelligence here at the
stole
um well i i would like to is it cheesy
to sort
of say like maybe put it to a vote or
just like see what the chat says and
what people are interested if people are
some some folks may be interested in
hearing about any of it and there's here
for the ride
others may say oh that what does that
mean
we could try um do this as a buffet i do
five minutes on every little thing or we
can go really deep on a couple of things
right is um so the question is uh like
do we talk about like one model like
deep dive into it and then go to another
um is there like a theme of uh um
like that you have like a taxonomy okay
this is this set of models
uh because i recall interviewing
gabrielle
uh weinberg who the ceo and founder of
duckduckgo he has this book super
thinking
and he has you know he collects all
these mental models there and he has
something called supermodels like models
that can apply cross domain and there's
ones that are more kind of like
contextually uh tethered
um so i'm wondering if you have a
taxonomy of these mental models
um and maybe that can kind of orientate
us to decide what
what to look at um
i don't have a taxonomy unfortunately um
if i spend a little more time i might be
able to
i was saying coloring or turning these
into boxes of like here's the
metaphysics part
here is the identity consciousness sort
of self
thing here are uh sociological things
here are technology and sociological
things here's technology by itself
and like there's there's kind of a way i
could there's one way to take it and
to use robert percy's um concept to take
the analytical knife
and slice this thing but i wouldn't say
that it's the only way to do it
um so
um i think the one that um maybe is
most for me the the most important one
to start with would be actually the
metaphysics of qual metaphysics of
quality
uh and and i'm sorry if everyone's
already read that and it's like kind of
old hat but
i feel like no one really talks about it
very much and i don't know that that's
because everyone already knows it or if
no one knows it
because you know conversations focus on
the new what do you think about that
yeah um i think that'd be good to double
click on that one
quite a few people were saying which
models you use most frequently and which
ones you found
uh most valuable so maybe that could be
another um
thread to pull on and then uh from
now till next week in the discord we can
kind of figure out
like i can send this powerpoint to
people we can figure out which ones they
would like and vote on it
uh well someone wanted to see the other
slide right so here's the other slide
and at this level of um structure or
object or whatever
there's there's a lot more things too i
just kind of threw up you know a couple
dozen things here
um but i'll start with the metaphysics
of quality because i feel like that is
something
a lot of our issues are metaphysical in
nature um if people
are interested uh there's that the uh
that freedom 2.0 blog post um on my
medium
is one i would um recommend people kind
of go through and read because i do talk
about the fact that we are coming
we are we have a philosophical crisis
you know the
the crisis and sense making is actually
because of a philosophical crisis
we don't even know how to define what is
and is not an object so we can't even
talk about relationships and theories of
objects because
our metaphysics is falling apart because
we have created new
kinds of pseudo-reality and this is
where it gets kind of into bodrillard
and the society of the spectacle and
hyper reality
um the the human consciousness that that
that lives
in modern society in the modern world
is is out of its metaphysical depth and
that explains a lot of confusion a lot
of the anger because when we're in
different
metaphysical corners that's a thousand
plateaus we can't even talk we can't
even bridge across each other because we
don't have a
common grounding of what reality is um
so i think somewhere here i have i have
that uh gosh where was it um
the speciation i call the speciation of
digital humans
um that that the those who live just in
the neocortical
um uh consciousness are
are speciating and not living embodied
lives uh and that makes it very very
easy to get
turned into just you know we're jacking
ourselves into the matrix which is a
concept i'm sure everyone here is
familiar with so
all right let me start with the
metaphysics of quality um because i
think this is a great
uh different metaphysics and i'm not
saying it's 100 right but i think it's a
really
useful lens to pick up on some kind of
signals so robert persig most famously
wrote
the book zen in the art of motorcycle
maintenance and
um in in that book he critiques what he
calls
the uh subject object metaphysics
and what that is is that this idea that
there's objective reality
and then we are all perceivers of
objective reality but on the side of it
outside of it
and and we have a subjective frame that
we understand objective reality in
and what he built out a little bit in um
he explored
why that kind of um classical approach
to it is
is is limiting in the book zen in the
art of moscow maintenance
and then in the in the um uh sequel
called lila he builds up what he calls
the metaphysics of quality
and it's an interesting project that he
undertook because he by
by developing a metaphysics in the way
he did
he it kind of had a a built-in ethical
system like a moral system that fell out
of it
which is interesting because that's to
say that wow we can just
the way we choose to define reality
itself has baked in values and morals
like that's a that's a kind of a weird
and interesting thing if it actually
works
so i just stole this picture from some
other dude who has a blog a vlog on
medium
about the metaphysical quality that is
probably worth going reading if this
interests you
but what he said is very simple he said
that the world consists
of really two things there's static
i'll define these words in a minute
there's static patterns of value and
there's dynamic
um uh there's there's sort of static
patterns
of value and there's this dynamic
quality
and what happens is that everything we
perceive what we call objective reality
rocks the sun um you know that fun
question of like
is there gravity is gravity a thing you
know the gravity exists before newton
like these kind of fun little philosophy
101 sort of questions
they they're they're uh confounding if
we use the classical
uh subject object metaphysics but in the
metaphysics of quality the idea is that
there are layers there are patterns and
then there's additional patterns that
build upon
those underlying patterns and within any
pattern within any particular
level of frequency or kind of level of
analysis
if you put energy into it then it will
seek to organize it'll create more
structure and it'll create
it basically becomes a substrate for
additional patterns another layer of
patterns on top
and so the the way he cleaved this he
sort of had four he called it sort of
four
uh roughly um uh layers
if you will of static patterns the very
basic one is what we would call the
physical
and the inorganic patterns and that is
things like rocks in the sun
you know the the computer that i'm on
here and of course all of the atoms and
molecules and everything inside your
body
on top of that there are biological
patterns
that are stable if the body if like
you're not in the middle of like a
plasma
ion cloud if you have stable physical
patterns like
atoms and molecules and they're kind of
interacting with each other and bouncing
around and their biochemistry and all
this stuff is happening
it actually gives rise to another layer
of patterns that are stable as well
and that's static pattern they form what
we call static patterns
like the um the cell wall of a cell or
like your bones
or whatever right so we have
each of these um layers if you will they
have their own homeostasis they have
their own sort of metabolism and
homeostasis they try to keep
and maintain structure if energy comes
in
that energy they take some of the energy
to maintain structure and the sun the
energy it's funneled into
then providing life or providing
dynamism at the next level up
and then on top of biological creatures
you build social and here's a very
important thing a super important
aspect of the metaphysic metaphysics of
quality
um things are don't just exist at one
pattern they exist across the stack
so you are not merely a pile of atoms
you are its yes and you are a pile of
atoms
and your biological creature and your
social creature and you are an
intellectual creature
and that idea that or the concept that
ideas have people
it's kind of this you are both a
vibrating buzzing collection of
trillions of atoms but at the same time
and you respond to light and i shine
enough light at you you
become a puff of like mostly oxygen
hydrogen and whatnot and carbon
but if i give you just enough light then
you get vitamin d which maintains
homeostasis for your body
which then you can become a vehicle for
balancing sound waves of other things
like you
and if you guys bounce the sound waves
off of each other there's another layer
of pattern
on top that we can get and that is the
intellectual pattern so there's our
intellectual layer
so the metaphysics of quality says we
are all of these things at once
and stability at one level gives rise as
a substrate
for patterns and dynamism the next level
every single layer
as you put energy into it it actually
surfaces something interesting at the
next layer and this is sort of a
critique as a physicist from the second
law of thermodynamics we say well in a
closed system
uh things will tend you know entropy
will increase and everything will just
kind of reach thermodynamic equilibrium
but that's for closed systems like the
earth is not a closed system you're not
a closed system i'm not a closed system
i'm having some you know tea in the
morning
so like what happens when there's energy
going to a non-closed system
well the physicists are useless about
this and yet this is literally every
system on earth
right there's no closed systems on earth
there's a lot of energy coming in
there's like gigawatts and gigawatts
booming at us from the sun
and that does stuff why don't we talk
about what that does and so the
metaphysics of quality
talks about sort of this and there's uh
i forget who was uh
shoot look at the name of the the
the guy who had that great quote that um
the flow of energy through a system
organizes the system
actually jim rutt like knows the guy
he's at santa fe institute uh
just his name slipped my mind but that
idea that when you do have energy the
way the energy flows
creates structure um which is an entire
like an antithetical concept
from those who have a surface like uh
who got like the the cliffs notes of the
second law of thermodynamics we're gonna
die heat death
well until we die he death what happens
right we get a bunch of energy from the
sun and all sorts of structure emerges
like you
you'd be hard-pressed to keep fungus
from growing if you put enough sunlight
and humidity on it right
so this is and so what what's important
about persig here
is that humans then we have a cult we
have a biological mode a physical mode
we also have a cultural mode that is
social
and then there's also an intellectual
mode and
when you have enough socialization and
this is kind of a cheesy view of the
world but but
you know it's i think directionally
correct when you have enough
socialization it gives rise to
intellectualization
but these are different things and and
right here i'll stop right here and give
you one example why this is useful
if we look at all of the arguments
around cancel culture right now we look
at all of the people like oh it's a free
speech
oh it's the left is becoming maoist red
guard is it this is it that
all of that confounding anger and
confusion and all these things i feel
like the conversation is quite broken
because people are basing on the wrong
metaphysics if you look at it from the
perspective of the metaphysics of
quality
what's offensive about using um
a social justice twitter mob to suppress
an idea
is that it inverts it's saying oh the
energy of the social
layer gets to define and and um abrogate
or sort of usurp the freedom
of the intellectual plane to explore
what it wants to do
and so in the same way that so it's so
percy in his book actually he lays out
um that his ethical or moral system is
that
it's unethical to kill or constrain
things
at the higher levels for the purposes of
the lower levels
right like you wouldn't go and say to
someone i'm sorry i have to kill you now
because i think your bones would make
really great they'd be very helpful
as a structural member in my retaining
wall right taking a biological thing
and using it to serve just a base
physical thing there is some kind of
harm done there there's some concept of
of
something bad and the and and where um
if you think about enlightenment
liberalism and this idea of intellectual
freedom
uh what we've done is we've said well
every person when they do pop their head
up into the intellectual
layer or when we analyze them as an
intellectual agent or entity
they should have freedom as an
intellectual entity to engage with
others at the intellectual layer
when you come in and say oh no no only
people of this of this particular social
cast
or only people have bridged through and
cross these particular social
gatekeepers by
you know kissing the right person
marrying the right person doing whatever
they then have a right to espouse an
intellectual idea
that itself is ethically wrong it's just
wrong and societies that structure
themselves themselves that way will be
ultimately they will be less capable
they'll be weaker they will be destroyed
by societies that orient themselves in
accord to this
so um every layer oh i didn't talk much
about dynamic quality every layer
when it gets energy it has a thing
called it shoots for dynamic
things at the layer above but it sort of
hits a plateau of what it's able to do a
plateau of complexity or
patterns it can you can sort of support
and so then the energy goes into forming
uh patterns to the next layer up and so
on so forth so this is kind of this
tiered step pyramid
if you will anyway so that was a lot
about that
one thing he did say was um this is
important uh he tends to view it
as a ratchet mechanism so what happens
is that the lower level
um a lower level pattern uh
layer when you get energy in a lot of
the homeostasis or a lot of the
metabolic systems at that layer
they're designed to allow um
innovation to kind of happen above while
trying to prevent
chaos and entropy from eroding it and
collapsing it to the layer below
and and he sees as he talks about as a
ratchet mechanism
and uh he gives an example in his book
about
a native american tribe um and the way
they cast this guy out
as uh as a as a freak um because he was
seen as a chaos agent and actually we
get this anyone plays d
d and and knows about alignments right
there's chaos chaotic evil
as well as chaotic good and the idea of
being lawful
is that you're part of the ratchet
you're lawful you're trying to keep this
thing from slipping backwards
and you cannot discern what of the chaos
is good and what the chaos is bad it's
just all beyond a fog beyond your ooda
loop beyond your
ability to discern you're just one of
these lawful people trying to keep
the trying to try to keep the tribe
alive right you just don't want to slip
back into chaos
and this same dynamic manifests and
pokes its head up
in a number of those things that i
showed on the very first slide you can
see it in the gervais theory
you can see it in a number of different
other things where
the forces of or actually uh shirky's
law right every institution
ultimately becomes uh perpetuates the
problem it was designed
to to solve right um and also in jerry
cornell's iron law of bureaucracy
uh all of these things they talk about
this ratchet mechanism essentially at
the social layer
an institution of bureaucracy or
whatever will tend to ossify
around the the defense of the ratchet
and that same thing that keeps it from
slipping backwards
also fights every possible innovation
agent because it sees it all as forces
of chaos
so that's that's another way that the
metaphysics of quality kind of you can
hear that mode resonating through all of
these other ideas
um that's why i think it's a very
important one and again it doesn't get
talked about very much
uh anymore because personally was a big
deal for maybe two generations back
not so much for our current generation
unfortunately
now one thing i would say though is that
when we think about it as a ratchet and
things like that it is again very easy
to think about
objects and things as being just at a
layer or this is a
this thing at the social layer this is
this thing at the biological layer
when in fact we have to remember it it
is waves of different frequencies all
overlapping all at once
all of us are little water molecules
everything in the world
is uh can be viewed as a stack of things
um it resonates at all of these
different layers so well i mean sorry
up to its top layer right so my camera
that i'm looking at right now is not a
biological thing
but it is um you know it is a it is a
physical object now where this gets
interesting when you talk about when you
look at it
when you look at some of these other
technological society
philosophers is that they would they
would sort of put an asterisk on that
and say well no
um a camera or a smartphone
or a sword or you know jared diamonds
guns from steel whatever
all of these inanimate objects that we
use that we call technology
they actually they they're not just our
static artifacts at the
physical layer they are in fact they
transform
these these these uh objects or beings
that exist at a social layer at the
intellectual layer
and so there is a lot more richness
than this is a simple chart but there's
a whole lot more interaction up and down
the stack a whole lot more ringing and
vibrating
than this kind of simple clean cut
pyramid
would uh would would imply so i'll stop
there
any questions about that how did that
how was that for you was that useful or
was it just me just spewing a bunch of
nonsense
like i quite liked it and people were
saying it's awesome and then the chats i
never heard of
this this model in particular so that
was quite a treat um
there's a few questions uh angen um
you have a clarifying question if you're
going to meet yourself and ask it to
peter
hey peter um i had a couple questions
but i guess i could start with the
clarifying one
um zero you could do that a little bit
slower i didn't quite understand the
quality fit in
or the ratchet or how like the
thermodynamics of
flow um meshed with the model
oh sorry the the concept of quality you
mean i
i just is there like an explanation five
version of what you just did
um let me think about how to yeah
i went through a lot of stuff so sorry
guys that was that was definitely just
like a spew of things
um the reason it's called the
metaphysics of quality
is because uh really it's a personal
story
that persic tells in his first book in
zen of the art of motorcycle maintenance
um and we tend to think of quality as an
adjective
right oh is this are you doing quality
work right um
and he was a professor at university of
montana bozeman
and his i guess his um secretary would
ask him every day just a nice old lady
you know good morning dr persig are you
do you know are you
are you doing quality are you teaching
quality today or something like that and
she'd keep asking this question and then
it's sort of he started thinking like
well what the hell's quality mean
what is good um all of us we use the
word quality and good as adjectives and
if there is a
pithy way of of saying the whole thing
um persec's idea here is that quality is
a noun
it's not that it's an adjective it's a
noun and all of these things he calls
them static patterns of value
you can also call them um static quality
versus dynamic quality
and our intuitive sense like if someone
gives you a piece of art
and says is this quality well you're
like well i don't know is it
are you just asking me to judge well i
like it so i guess yes
we are setting ourselves in a subject
object metaphysics mind to say well
there's objective properties i could say
is this art piece is a sculpture blue
and you would say yes of course it's
blue um i would say is it transparent
and you say no it's not transparent it's
solid blue right and i'd say is it
quality and you would say well that's
subjective i think it's quality you may
not think it's quality
and this is what's called the subject
object metaphysics but if you think
about this a little bit more
you know is it blue well kind of depends
on you know the actual receptors in your
in your eyeball it also is a transparent
depends on if you're looking at it in
the um
radio frequency right or if you're
looking at it in light and
there's actually a lot of these
characteristics that we think are
objective that are
actually subjective properties and and
then the real like brain
kind of twist is to say that a lot of
things that we think of as subjective
properties
and this is where it gets a little
post-modern but uh especially that
quality of or that property of like
is it good is it quality there his
metaphysics of quality
is actually taking this perspective that
quality is an
objective thing if you will it's a noun
things have
quality to them and when they get energy
they try to build more quality but they
hit a certain level and the next level
of quality
things they can emerge they have a
different structure to them and there's
layers there's a layer cake
of quality but it's all it's like it's
all good it's all goodness
and and it's a really and i can't
summarize two books in just like five
minutes
but that's you you can disagree with
that you said that sounds like a pile of
crap like a bunch of pomo whatever
but it's a very interesting lens to put
on to look at the world to say
what if the world and and for those of
you who are maybe um
uh believe in you know have some kind of
spirituality uh that you're interested
in
um what if the world actually is trying
to express
godliness what if it's actually striving
for good
as an absolute value because
like i said life is interestingly
unstoppable when you start putting
energy into things
if you we see wolfram's book right just
in the raw math
on iterated systems and cellular
automata
patterns emerge where did that come from
and you know when um pat ryan was on
uh maybe a couple months ago and he
talked about hyper real numbers having a
life to them
this is where it gets into that
metaphysical aspect of like whoa
what if the very structure of reality is
that it's
everything is striving for good but they
strive for it not in a linear fashion
but in this kind of stag
sort of a cigarette fashion right um
wow that's actually a very weird way to
look at the world but
it gives you some tools that are not
available if you don't use that
approach to say that this you know we
can actually say
you know this is this is what um ethical
harm looks like here's what ethical good
looks like on the basis of are we
promoting
more life more goodness more quality are
we letting things strive for dynamic
quality
from within their static plane i don't
know if that helped if that confused
things but but the the net net is that
quality is a noun not an adjective
and then your comment about
thermodynamics and
adding energy to a system how does that
fit this striving towards goodness
well um yeah the way it fits is that um
the and he actually does talk about this
in his book as well uh that
when we think about systems and the
behavior of systems um
uh we we we know about the second law of
thermodynamics which says that
closed systems will eventually erode
into or a road
they'll decay into just everything is an
evil equal temperature background noise
of like nothing
or of like you know just background
everything's undifferentiated high
entropy
now uh what he says the critique is well
what what if there's not what is not a
closed system what if we look at a thing
we say well
we can draw some you know dashed lines
and say here's a system but it's getting
energy in
it's getting energy pumped in what
happens in a non-closed system
and what happens is structure emerges
almost
always and everywhere so you can talk
about spin glasses you can look at
theory of chaos you can look at cellular
automata
and those are kind of mathematical
things if you look at the physical world
around you
right um he has a great i've forgotten
now but in this book he talks about
chemistry professors
sitting on rocks baking in the sun and
it's like the theory of thermodynamics
if it's a closed system says that
things just decay into pile of goo but
what we actually see is that the earth
produces him one of my favorite quotes
from
when i was a freshman in college i
discovered this quote that stuck with me
all my life
and it says that um it's also one of
these like little brain
brain teaser things uh man was invented
by water
to carry itself uphill
and that statement is true here's the
here's the f'd up thing that statement
is true
and it also talks it's this man was
invented
by water to carry itself uphill
let that sit with you for a little bit
and that's why this stands in contrast
with the second law of thermodynamics
because in in non-equilibrium states if
you
look at what happens you get a whole lot
of water making man
and so that's an interesting thing and
so his metaphysical quality is to talk
about at least give us a starting point
to talk about
what are the layers of structure as
energy flows through a system and
organizes the system
what do those organizations look like
and they tend to have this kind of
pattern that's where the ratchet
is so important that they will surface
things things will emerge patterns will
emerge
they'll stabilize but the same thing
that stabilizes that pattern and keeps
it alive
and fights off the forces of entropy
trying to reduce it back down to nothing
it is also fighting the forces of
innovation and things that might take it
to the next level
and what bridges it across that that you
know what gets us that next hump
um that's you might hear you know brett
weinstein or jordan talking about
crossing an adaptive valley right jim
rod same thing we talk about crossing
adaptive valley we talk about that
in the in the context of evolutionary
systems and biology and biological
systems but
med but the person's metaphysics talks
about this as a fundamental
general kind of thing so you can look at
it as as face structured and crystalline
solids you can look at
you know metastable things and and spin
glasses it's it's a really fascinating
thing
uh when you start looking at
non-equilibrium dynamics
does that again does that help answer do
you have a follow-on
if you don't mind me a quick follow-on
to paraphrase so basically if you like
pour energy into an open system
and you kind of just jump like you know
you're
shaking the puzzle box you'll just start
to see some puzzle pieces fit together
per sig's point is the way that things
fit together and then emerge
into a layer and then emerge into a
layer um
there's kind of like a teloteleological
like it's almost like going towards
goodness yes his way of calling goodness
is quality
yes exactly and every layer has its own
view of what that goodness is
and the same its own view of goodness
that defends itself and keeps it from
collapsing back
actually also impedes the next layer of
goodness emerging
and that's what the ratchet is that's
what the ratchet is exactly and and as
you were talking about it as you pour
energy into a system i just thought
about this um
wonderful setup maybe you guys have seen
this in science museums but um i i first
saw it at the
science museum in berlin but you can
just take a piece of flat uh
piece of like thin sheet of sheet metal
and you pour a bunch of random sand on
it if you take
a cello bow a cheap one hopefully and
you just like
strum it along the side at a freak at a
constant frequency
on the side of this metal plate you'll
get patterns you'll get shapes of sand
they'll dance and if you vary the
frequency they'll shift
and they'll sort of form one pattern and
then as you do it kind of at a higher
frequency it'll sort of like be kind of
messy and they'll shift into another
pattern
you can also look for youtube videos of
what happens when people put plates
or glass or thin things on top of a
speaker and they pour sand on and they
turn on the speaker to some
high-pitched pure sinusoidal wave and
you see the pattern shifting around
that's that's essentially this thing um
and this is what ties into then
four dimensionalism time frequency and
the metaphysical basis of reality
and the temporality of it um that's
that's also tied to this a little bit
they get another deep kind of
metaphysical connection
but but yes you summarize very well
thank you both peters feel free
to boot me from asking another follow-up
but i think i'm missing why the ratchet
emerges like why is it this inevitable
thing
i don't know but it seems to um i see it
in
in organizations i try to sell them
software i see it in communities you see
it in in uh human
societies i mean it's an aspect of human
socialization but i feel like if i
if i try to uh use this and look at the
world this way i can see a lot of things
i use as a hammer i find a lot of nails
it's interesting why isn't just a smooth
continuous linear thing all the way up
to goodness
right i don't know good question
all right um rain you had a few
questions
and statements uh is anything still
alive for you just wanted to check in
um my question was answered so if there
are other questions go for it
all right
i don't see any okay
uh margaret you got a question
yeah my question is i'm hearing and i'm
trying to assess how accurate my
understanding is but an implication
that flow is largely unidirectional
and not in that the exact direction is
uh determined but the general like
flow of movement of what you're talking
about of the order flowing up
through the layers giving rise to other
layers and then trying to prevent
entropy and chaos
in the lower layers that there is this
general sense
of movement in a specific direction and
though it may be possible to
work against that there's like a lot of
energy incentives
to move with that flow is that accurate
at all
um it's uh it's a it's a very good
statement
that um helps to illustrate why my
description was a bit flawed
and so so i would say that the um the
thing i didn't articulate
i think maybe very clearly is that um
even though we talk about patterns
emerging and uh and and it's it's it's
hard with language not to have
um sort of latent value when we talk
about oh this is going up
and it's higher and therefore it's
better um the idea here is that
these things all the
these patterns emerge stacked on top of
each other
and so it's it's more of an emergence
it's like does
this system did it emerge a biological
sort of homeostatic uh homeostasis layer
and if it did that
does this system it's almost like you're
playing the game spore and you start
with like some like you know gray goo
or like little protozoa and they try to
form multicellular societies and things
like that
it's it's um again with our subject
object metaphysics we try to take a
knife and cut the world into things with
boundaries
and you're either a thing or not a thing
um
but what the metaphysics of quality
encourages you to think about and that's
why i have a picture of water waves
is that if you're a molecule in the
water you can have waves of many
different frequencies all
going through you at once right if you
think about a point
um you know at the intersection of these
two ripple patterns that point
is part of both waves at the same time
and in here
when that energy comes in um new
kinds of patterns one could call them
higher order modes or
or higher frequency or they require a
certain higher amount of energy in order
to sustain themselves
um and in that way they're higher
like you don't get there unless you put
higher amounts of energy and sustain
that at some frequency
but um but that's that's what so there's
not a flow
up like that it's more of these patterns
emerge does that make sense
yeah yes it does and thank you for that
reframe um
i was using the flow up because i was
looking at that pyramid model yeah
exactly i guess maybe my my question
which one i'm hearing is that it's not
like the direction itself is not
important but that there is
i guess what i'm trying to clarify is
what i hear is that there's directional
movement happening
within like if you're talking about a
cellular level on that level but there's
also this
overall sense of movement that's
happening for
all the interconnected layers which has
a general vector um and then within that
larger
like collection there's also all these
different directional movements
happening on
many different levels and interacting
yes yes there's um there's a
uh yes
one something you said there in the
middle
um
it is it is that the lower levels will
give rise to higher levels right and the
higher levels will try to sap energy and
organize the lower levels and this
interplay this is that that struggle and
the tension in the ratchet
um and so but it all ha it's all the
same time
it's sort of and and we can see
ourselves in as individuals
um being part of like if you ask what
was my identity well i have a
i've i'm this particular part of
physical space if you take a knife and
cut off one of my fingers i would say
well part of i'm a lesser me now
because i'm losing if i've lost a finger
but i'm also
a node in an intellectual network i'm a
person in a social kind of
uh cohesive thing here you know my
family and so i'm all of these all at
once
and i'm allocating energy across these
in my own
embodied life and this is where this
then kind of takes us maybe as a segue
to the next topic about how this ties to
identity
every human being is all of these all at
once
right you can't ignore your physical
safety and your physical self i mean in
a sense this does mirror maslow's
hierarchy a little bit
right you want to defend your physical
space and the physical integrity of your
being
then there's the biological integrity
like if you really got to go use the
bathroom or if you're really really
hungry and you need to eat
there's a biological integrity if you
need to breathe you're going to really
work to get more oxygen right
but then above that there's there's
social needs and there's an intellectual
dynamic that that we have
and all of these things are flowing
through us at once and we have to manage
the interplay of these things
um we can't just be all living in our
forebrain being like i'm just this
avatar on twitter
and look how many upvotes and likes i
have or look how many instagram
followers i got
you're not living an embodied life and
you're ignoring these other needs and
you're allocating energy up into
a social pseudo-intellectual kind of
level
so this is this is i think if you think
about the embodied
self like in the whole human self it's
also a good way to understand
that it's not just energy going into
only going up but it's it's allocating
and balancing
the energies and energy allocations
across the whole stack does that make
sense
that does thank you yes great
um should we should we any other
comments that you want to highlight
peter or
um so we have about 10 minutes of a lot
of time we can go a little bit over
it's up to you we have enough more
questions or you want to um
well i'll just put this picture up
because this is exactly to uh i'm sorry
was a margaret that was just speaking
um yes yes margaret so this is sort of a
picture i had
uh for that kind of speaks to this point
about um
you know this little oval is meant to
represent
uh the self each of us and these
different colored
circles are um modes or components or
ways of being
at different layers and different levels
of the the persig metaphysics
uh so we have different biological needs
we have different social needs and
intellectual things
and there's tension between them they
kind of jostle around
um we are really a society of self uh
but anyway let's put that picture up
there okay i mean
uh other other questions and thoughts i
can go and touch on a different topic
now we've covered
the metaphysics of quality um so we have
about
nine minutes left you want to end it off
with one more question and we can kind
of figure out
oh sure yeah let's do that yeah uh rain
uh i believe you you've dropped two
questions um
in the chat yeah now the first one
should be pretty quick
um is this like pretty uh kind of basic
integral theory all quadrants all levels
all lines
right the the um quadra i forget what
word he uses
that everything manifests within
inner outer uh singular plural
yes i think there's uh yes i when i and
i have not
gone deep on integral theory and it's
been a little while i actually
i've got the little chart uh it was just
sort of related to
oh actually the green is filling in
there
but um but i think yes the
from what i recall as i was first
looking into integral theory
there was definitely a lot of resonance
with these concepts um
and i don't know how much i mean if
there was an influence or not i i don't
really know but
um but yeah i think i think those those
concepts are quite are those
kind of bodies of work are quite
resonant with each other
yeah it seems like they're they're both
tapping into
ideas that go back to um
the neoplatonists and and then later
um de chardin and orobindo
um like the hierarchy of being sounds
right right right
i've actually forgotten much of the dish
i did now but one of the
um one of the things that unfortunately
i think personally does not spend as
much time talking about is you know
there's just so much subtlety
and nuance oh what's going on come on
um within that the social cultural
intellectual
stacks there's so much nuance um of the
interactions there
um he doesn't spend as much time talking
about developing
a model of the human psyche uh although
ironically he spends most the first book
talking about his own mental breakdown
in
electroshock therapy uh but in terms of
what like uh metzinger would talk about
thomas messinger and his model of
uh the ego tunnel and um the emergence
of consciousness right or
um you know a lot of the more modern uh
writings about
um the self and selfhood um
because our our so much of our um
sense of self emerges from our
interaction
in the cultural mode in the social media
that
if we don't model the medium uh a lot of
what we think about is our
as as my identity is actually a space
that's carved out
by the society around us with a label on
it saying this is you
this is what society thinks is you and
whether you want to habit it or not and
you might feel you might feel resentment
at it because you're constrained
you might feel stressed because it's too
big right whatever it might be
but they don't i mean personally doesn't
talk about that stuff at all i think
there's a lot of rich of course a lot of
huge rich amount of discourse around
around those kinds of things
so unfortunately this framework is not
so informative for
understanding you know the details of
some of that
all right so look five minutes left i'm
cool
after cool peter for another like 10 15
minutes after
absolutely yeah did you want to jump
into another model
yeah let me see here um the another one
uh i could talk about here is
let's pick another one
so um
since we set up now the metaphysics of
quality
i'll talk about the arc heidi smith
model
and that's a term that i am i mean it's
a term that jordan
hall coined and i i i don't think it's
gotten as much press as it should
because it's a really fantastic
um the heidi smith there is um bryce
heidi smith
and um and uh jordan coined this in one
of his like early video blog things he
did
um and the arc heidi smith model uh says
that there's
sort of three types of human disposition
within a society
um there are the people who are what he
calls the um
the wild type and these are people who
go out into
like they go into the forest they'll go
into the wilds and they will go and
cut things to cut down trees and kill
you know scary animals
and build build something build a living
build a safe place
build society in the in the wilderness
in the jungle
then there's the domestic type who once
you have a city
once you have palaces once you have
palace guards and coinage and all these
rules and laws and
all these different things and gallows
to hang people
once you have all the stuff the domestic
type really likes living in the city
they navigate the structure of uh human
political intrigue
they um weave into subjective reality
right they
they're very familiar and comfortable at
that layer if you put them out in the
jungle
they're they hate it their toast their
toast they cannot actually think outside
of the structures that
you know they like to be in those
structures i've called them you know you
might call them bureaucrats right
you might call them mandarins um
whatever they are
they're kind of that domesticated uh
bureaucrat management class
and then there's the um feral type
and the the the feral type what they do
is they live within domestic
environments
but they are chaos agents they they are
there spraying the graffiti on the walls
they're there
uh you know tearing things down and it's
one could argue is it a manifestation of
freudian suppression is it
um a wild type that is not given enough
wild room to roam
you know what is it but those three kind
of modes of being
um is what at least you know i'm hearing
secondhand essentially from jordan how
he characterizes the arc heidi smith
model
of society and um
and it ties a little bit to uh if you're
familiar with jonathan hates moral
foundation theory
that some people are uh they have a they
have what they see as being morally
virtuous
is you know law and order respect for
hierarchy respect for ancient tribal
elders and
tradition uh you see yourself as part of
an unbroken chain of all these ancestors
before you
there's that kind of moral foundation
there's others the moral foundation is
individual freedom
and and you could be you know on the
right or on the left but there's a
manifestation of like
or there's a a sense that i
should have the right to do whatever the
f i want to and you're not going to stop
me
and i'm just a rebel without a cause or
maybe a rebel with a cause it doesn't
matter i'm just a rebel not me
so you better like it and so um
these different moral foundations uh
different
everyone has a little mix of all of
these different things right there's a
fairness one there's a virtue one
there's
you know sorry there's a fairness
there's um there's
individual liberty um there's um law and
order
etc now um if you look at the arc heidi
smith model then
a lot of the current things that we deal
with especially in this era of trump and
antifa and blm and all this other stuff
um uh you know we can sort of see it
refracted through that lens
of the arc heidi smith but another thing
that is interesting to refract
that lens is um when um
uh eric weinstein talks to peter thiel
and and he talks about
um he talks about um the great
stagnation
right since the 70s uh the institution's
been captured they're underserving us
um what's going on we're just paying the
piper now like you know i don't like
trump but
he's just kind of what you get if you
basically fail at institutions and
growth for 40 years
and pretend everything's fine right so
from that critique perspective you can
also see it from our heidi smith model
that
we have been overrun overbuilt by
bureaucrats
who have fended off innovation and um
collapse
with the same they can't discern between
the two
and you could see this i mean as i'm
saying this i can almost see myself like
what was that book about hillary
clinton's uh disastrous 2016 campaign
it's that kind of thing where we know
we're doing
we're the experts here and anyone who's
worked a big company who's had to deal
with a bunch of management consultants
coming in
you've probably seen the exact same
thing the archives with model again
you have the the wild type the
entrepreneurs that go out and build
um the frontiersmen whatever have you um
then you've got
the domestic class who really just like
being in the city and running the rules
and procedures and being like all the
chaos agents go outside
please and then you've got the feral
type who are just like f all of this
this is all
this is all left up we are kali we are
the creators we are the destroyers right
or we're the destroyers
uh kali is destroyer not his creator in
that case and so
um and you can see this in that you can
see this in um actually vancat's uh
gervais theory the reason kind of wrote
it right under your base theory
within um companies maybe next time i'll
talk about your base theory a little bit
more which is
fantastic for those who are not familiar
with it um but within companies you've
got sociopaths at the top
you've got the clueless in the middle
and you've got the um
the uh the losers the people who know
they have no franchise in the system at
the bottom
and your domestic class kind of the
mandarins um
in the in the heidi smith model they're
in that middle they're in the middle to
keep the other people kind of
in line so you can see reflections of
bryce of bryce heidi smith's uh thinking
through many of these other things as
well so i'll leave it at that any
questions or or comments on that
do you see this mapping over to uh
samuel bergeron's uh
kind of live player dead player uh
distinction
if you're familiar with that i'm not
that familiar with it can you can you
just give me like the yeah essentially a
live player
is someone uh as an individual a group
of people who can create things that
haven't been created before in a dead
player because basically only can follow
a script
um and so i'm wondering if that maps
over to the the wild entrepreneurial
type
or can a domestic person be a live
player too in a certain context
well this is where this is great that's
that's fantastic
so they are a live player at a different
level
right they're playing at defending the
static level down here
the wild type the live player in that
framework as you described it
they're pushing liveness up to the next
layer they're trying to explore what
options are available at the next layer
here and the live player in
what might be called a dead player i
guess they're actually a live player
within the strata
right um uh susan you had a question
about mental models and more foundation
or any other question you'd like to ask
um yes uh so
i guess that question alone in terms of
um is do you see a difference between
um and when i say moral foundations i'm
not talking about a particular theory as
much as i am
um the uh just the you know the
the when we get into moral foundations
to me
it sounds like we're starting to get
into
a a more nuanced
view that actually is
more about ideals and you know when we
get into you know
the ideal of what we were just talking
about in terms of
uh where somebody values compliance for
example
that's do you see that kind of as being
you know a a node within mental models
but is there a way to
to take that up a level i mean what
where i'd kind of like to see
right where i'm kind of
fascinated with is how we get people to
move from um just perspective
taking to perspective seeking
uh-huh and um and and i love your
passion
about all of this and so it was like if
we could just kind of bottle that
and get people excited about um how do
you
what is the value to you because i think
that a lot of people kind of
when they hear these terms they kind of
shut down because they think well
you know i'm stupid because i don't know
that and and so yeah that
all of a sudden their energy starts
getting wrapped up in their own
shame and ignorance and that's not the
point so
can you speak to that yes absolutely um
and i'll go and i'll go in sequence here
um so the first thing you asked about
the moral foundation theory i do mean
that in a very precise sense of jonathan
hates
uh in his book uh the righteous mind um
which
is uh just uh it was fantastic um and
he identifies uh he says you know we
tend to think about oh well and this you
know the subtitle for that book is
why good people are divided by politics
and religion right i mean you know
person a
thinks that they're standing up for
these virtues person b thinks they're
stand for these virtues why they hate
each other's guts
right literally they're shooting each
other in the streets yeah and
it's we don't recognize it's almost like
if we argue if food is delicious or not
so he's sort of
this is a little pomo because it's
saying there isn't an absolute like this
is absolutely the right way to think
about the world
right and he actually is a liberal guy
who went to
think from chicago and he went to um he
studied in india and looked at the
structure society there
where there you know respect for the
family is so important in the eastern
cultures right you are not an individual
really you are
a node in an unbroken chain in a family
unit
and the family's needs are really
important part of what you should be
doing
so that's so different than the american
model of individuality
um but he went and studied this and he
wrote this book
and he called and i've shared on the
screen here the five moral foundations
and he describes it as almost like
flavors like we go into different parts
of the world you get food that's
different flavors
and there's no saying that thai food is
the wrong flavor and cajun food is the
right flavor right
it's just that we are trained to taste
certain kinds of flavors in fact think
about food in certain kinds of flavors
and a lot of eastern cooking has umami
in it that umami flavor has a sick
flavor right kind of was all over the
foodie
web in the last you know over 10 years
so in his sense it's um
he talks about these five foundations
and then they have um they have an
opposite thing like a thing that
that is the if you lack that particular
moral thing if you violate that that
moral foundation
and what you identify was actually
there's two higher order clusters
so there's a person focused there's a
very uh individual focused
individualizing cluster care
fairness that tends to be what the the
modern liberal
kind of mentality is those on the left
the progressives
there's a very strong obsession with
fairness but then there's a
binding cluster as well people who want
loyalty authority sanctity purity
um that's another cluster and in fact
and so he looks at kind of it's a great
book i would just recommend you know if
you're interested reading that
um these moral foundations do give rise
to
other things right so we can use this
and incorporate this thinking
until we look at the arc heidi smith
model the people who sit there and
defend
um they defend the domesticated class
the bureaucrats
you know there's bureaucrats on both
moral sides
right on the one side you might have a
bureaucrat or a domestic type saying
we need to do it this way because this
is fair this is this is the fair way to
do it someone else might say we do it
this way because we've always done away
this is the way the founding fathers
wrote it and intended it
right it's tradition um and in both
cases though they're domestic class
because they're saying
it's it's it's uh it's it's sort of um
holding the status quo a little bit
right so you can sort of combine this
with the other it's not like
um again it adds the flavor of the
analysis
there's another thing you talked about
which is that how do we get people to be
perspective seeking
and this does then tie to um
the um
well one of the things here let me share
this screen let's share again
oh my god is there a way to save the
chat logs because i do want to go back
and read all of them but i
haven't uh yeah i can send it to you
okay that's fantastic
um and then we can talk about them in
the discord i love discord so
um here so when it comes to the
perspectives and getting people to
to be comfortable thinking about all the
stuff and getting into all this stuff
um when we think about the the stack of
like the metaphysics of quality
or master's hierarchy when you just go
with maslow if you're not uh
stable at the bottom layers right if you
have needs or if you have childhood
traumas
or you have constant present traumas
all of these things make it really hard
for you to have smooth sailing
and to go and reach out and be open
right because
you're using all of your energy
emotional psychic physical
all of it to maintain homeostasis like
to be just a coherent human being
you're trying to you know drive
resonance between all these different
layers of yourself
um or drive just maintain coherence
between these different layers of
yourself
um and if we can basically
create a social structure that doesn't
harm children
and doesn't traumatize them uh then we
can build a cycle of goodness
uh this is there's a little line i have
in the next slide here where i say
quality generativity is quality that
attracts quality
my view on game b and jim rutt has um
uh generously um uh not generously but
he's i'm very glad to see that he's also
reflected some of this
uh the the goal of the game the effort
now is to create
some infrastructure to allow us to be
good parents to the next generation
to create people to create children that
are not already marked from the get-go
with a lot of trauma that leads to
narcissism that leads to codependency
that leads to
um bonker mentality and seeking
epistemic closure just sucking our own
thumbs and sucking their own
you know just sucking their own phone
screens you have to get people
into basic coherence across the basic
layers before they can be open
to the exploring out and really this is
then no different than anything keegan
said right the key of model human
development
if people are stuck in keegan 3 or 2
they're not going to be thinking outside
their current perspectives that keegan
five level
um and it's it's not a perfect model but
it's essentially the same thing
does that answer your question or
address the comment
uh yeah yeah it um you know
what i do want to just point out that i
find it interesting that that
particular model you showed um nowhere
on it
is is freedom oh it actually
it is sorry let me let me share it again
it is there um
wrong one see this window
the liberty foundation a sixth
foundation liberty
was theorized okay in response to the
need to differentiate between
proportionality fairness
um yeah and coercion by dominating power
so interesting yeah
yes very cool i think what's interesting
is within any of these
foundations um
you can see all of the arc heidi smith
um
behaviors manifesting uh out of a desire
to optimize for one of these moral
foundations so these things are
you can do a cartesian product it's not
like one subsumes the other
um so someone in service of fairness can
go and be a domesticated power structure
sort of like preserving thing
um or you can be the wild type to say
i'm gonna go and seek fairness
just directly with empathy out in the
world with people right so
this yeah and i guess that that's kind
of where
it and yeah this is uh maybe a myopic
view but
but the if we if we talk about mental
models
um then for me it's almost
um moral agnostic because
once we start interjecting these
particular morals
then that's taking us down a rabbit hole
in terms of
what morals are right or wrong
do you agree with that um
sort of so the reason for sharing
the moral foundations theory is that
i think it is a good mental model
because then you can help understand
what's motivating this person why
do they disagree with me um it's a it's
a
way to use a richer language to talk
about and get through this agreement so
that's why i think the moral foundations
theory itself
is is a mental model when we talk about
specific things being good or bad you're
right that's um
no longer an agnostic tool however
it's not clear to me that the agnostic
tools are necessarily the right ones
what if there actually is a moral order
to the universe
and i'm not doubting that i'm just
trying to and maybe yeah maybe
where what comes to mind for me is
saying you know maybe
maybe what i'm talking about is more of
a meta meta model
okay and you're in and so there's you
know there's
obviously many many mental models and
you know
in fact if you just say that as someone
who's completely
not a prospective seeker then
they're going to say my mental model is
right and yours wrong and automatically
we've lost the
the essence of where we're trying to
take that conversation
yes oh yeah that makes that makes total
sense um
[Music]
these are these are so so i promise in
the first slide a bestiary
and access to tools right this is a
fantastic conversation
i think that i'm just kind of um yeah
going
this this is fascinating and you've done
a fantastic job of pulling this together
so thank you
thank you i will you know i will say one
thing that um
in my freedom 2.0 uh blog post i do talk
about
the tools we must use actually
specifically addressing this question
um if you're gonna find it
aha okay let me share and then uh oh
come on where is it share new share
um here so in this blog post
um so i say the process what's needed
for phase change in human civilization
is a new set of narratives about agency
dignity and even the meaning of humanity
itself
at the individual and collective level
one of the one of the more i think
dangerous and controversial things i put
on um
my slide of of uh of um
you know my my bcr here is the idea that
networks have rights
i don't hear anyone else really saying
that i think that networks
and to some extent i think corporations
should be more people like and should be
treated more people like
um which you do not hear anyone else in
this kind of
environment but the thing i say here is
that in order for this culture for this
effort to succeed for the the physics or
a freedom 2.0 conception succeed
we must develop a process that gives
rise to new flavors of culture
that move away from tribal leanings and
in most situations
it has to engage with existing cultures
via two weapons
confusion and delight confused to jam
the
loop of the the domestic class locking
you into the current
strata and delight to tune people in to
turn them on to the idea that there's
something
above that they take the energy as
opposed to focusing it inward to
tribalism and defense
and bunker mentality and protection they
can take that energy to something above
so hopefully that addresses your answers
your question
i love that i love it can you put that
in the chat yes i'll directly link it
here
stop share chat
okay all right
awesome thank you susan
yeah thanks everyone for participating
in engagement and some of the great
comments and questions i really really
appreciated that yeah that was uh really
fun peter um
so any thoughts on how we should
structure next week
um yeah let's see how the discord goes
let's play it by ear and just be
you know i think we're gonna have a lot
of fun in the discord and then um
next next week i mean i think
it would be if i get my my thoughts and
stuff together on paper
um a good description and discussion of
four dimensionalism
um the uh maybe a little preview of the
gervais theory for people who
you know are not familiar with this are
really great um
yeah a couple of things like that might
be fun uh one one sort of
thought and question for everyone to
ponder as we wrap this up
is you know what does it mean for
something
can we really observe and perceive
something that happens only once
um and my uh my
my my thesis is that the the human brain
fundamentally operates on frequencies
and something happens only once has an
infinite frequency or a
non-defined frequency you're waiting for
the next thing to happen again
but but the world is nothing but
a sequence of singular events and our
patterning engine requires
structures and repetition and patterns
and frequencies
so this gets to the four dimensionalism
and to thinking about temporality force
landry some good some of this but
i'll just leave everything with that
question can we really perceive
something that happens
once zero one infinity
very cool um so thank you peter uh for
coming today
and for kicking kick starting this um
since making residence
all right here's the the links uh for
there's a link to the discord um and i
was thinking
like i i do this thing called on anki on
my phone
sex uh it's like yeah memorization tool
for space repetition they use trace
repetition to help memorize
i have like my mental models on there
and i kind of do it it's sort of like a
rhizome when you have like one mental
model following another then you find a
connection between two and just triggers
things
so it'd be cool um if someone wants to
create like a mental model like
channel and the discord and then we kind
of collect some mental models that
peter's talking about we find our own
and maybe have some exercises or
workshops around it i'd be really down
for that if someone
is eager to take the lead either here or
listening um
and so yeah check out upcoming events
here's one that i'll plug
uh brett weinstein is coming in to talk
about unity 2020
september 21st uh that's gonna be a wild
day because we have zack stein coming in
derek jensen and alexander dugan oh and
then brett weinstein all in one day
so that's gonna be a delicious day
and then stoa if you'd like to support
us you can check out the patreon
page page which i've posted above that
being said
peter thanks so much and everyone thank
you all